that it is possible to transmit a video
بأنه يمكن ارسال فيديو
from a standard off-the-shelf LED lamp
من مصباح يعمل بنظام الليد
to a solar cell with a laptop acting as a receiver.
الى خلية شمسية باستخدام كمبيوتر محمول يعمل كجهاز الاستقبال.
There is no Wi-Fi involved, it's just light.
لا يوجد تدخل لل واي-فاي فقط ضوء
And you may wonder, what's the point?
وقد تتسائل, ما الفائدة ؟
And the point is this:
و الفائدة هي :
There will be a massive extension of the Internet
سيكون هناك تمديدات ضخمة للانترنت
to close the digital divide,
لسد الفجوة الرقمية,
and also to allow for what we call "The Internet of Things" --
و أيضا للسماح بما نسميه " إنترنت الأشياء " -
tens of billions of devices connected to the Internet.
عشرات المليارات من الأجهزة متصلة بالإنترنت.
In my view, such an extension of the Internet can only work
من وجهة نظري مثل هذه الاضافة للانترنت يمكن فقط ان تعمل
if it's almost energy-neutral.
اذا لم تحمل بطاقة زائدة
This means we need to use existing infrastructure as much as possible.
هذا يعنى استخدام البنية التحتية الموجوده قدر الامكان
And this is where the solar cell and the LED come in.
وهنا ياتي دور الخلية الشمسية ومصابيح الليد
I demonstrated for the first time,
لقد عرضت للمرة الاولى
at TED in 2011,
في TED عام 2011
Li-Fi, or Light Fidelity.
خدمة اللاي-فاي او العمل وفق الضوء
Li-Fi uses off-the-shelf LEDs to transmit data incredibly fast,
يستخدم لاي-فاي مصابيح ليد لنقل البيانات بسرعة رهيبة
and also in a safe and secure manner.
وايضا باسلوب امن
Data is transported by the light,
تنقل البيانات من خلال الضوء
encoded in subtle changes of the brightness.
مشفرة بترميزات متغيرة
If we look around, we have many LEDs around us,
لو نظرنا حولنا لوجدنا العديد من لمبات الليد
so there's a rich infrastructure of Li-Fi transmitters around us.
اذا هناك بنية تحتية غنية بموصلات الليد
But so far, we have been using special devices -- small photo detectors,
لكن حتى الان، نحن نقوم باستخدام اجهزة خاصة -- كاشفات صور صغيرة
to receive the information encoded in the data.
لاستقبال المعلومات المشفرة من خلال البيانات
I wanted to find a way to also use existing infrastructure
لقد اردت ايجاد طريقة ايضا من اجل استخدام البنية التحتية الحالية
to receive data from our Li-Fi lights.
من اجل استقبال البيانات عن طريق اللاي-فاي
And this is why I have been looking into solar cells and solar panels.
ولهذا السبب كنت ابحث في الخلايا والوحدات الشمسية
A solar cell absorbs light and converts it into electrical energy.
الخلية الشمسية تمتص الضوء وتحوله الى طاقة كهربية
This is why we can use a solar cell to charge our mobile phone.
لذلك نحن نستطيع استخدام خلية شمسية لشحن تليفوننا المحمول
But now we need to remember
لكن نحتاج لان نتذكر
that the data is encoded in subtle changes of the brightness of the LED,
ان البيانات مشفرة بترميزات متغيرة من ضوء الليد
so if the incoming light fluctuates,
لذلك اذا تذبذب الضوء القادم للخلية
so does the energy harvested from the solar cell.
ايضا نفس الحال بالنسبة للطاقة المستخلصة من الخلية الشمسية
This means we have a principal mechanism in place
هذا يعني اننا نمتلك الالية الرئيسية
to receive information from the light and by the solar cell,
لاستقبال المعلومات من الضوء ومن خلال الخلية الشمسية
because the fluctuations of the energy harvested
لأن تذبذبات الطاقة المستخلصة
correspond to the data transmitted.
مسؤولة عن ايصال البيانات
Of course the question is:
طبعا السؤال هو
can we receive very fast and subtle changes of the brightness,
هل يمكن اسقبال تغيرات مرمزة وبسرعة عالية من خلال الضوء الساطع
such as the ones transmitted by our LED lights?
مثل تلك التي تصلنا من خلال مصابيح الليد؟
And the answer to that is yes, we can.
والاجابة على ذلك هي ، نعم نستطيع
We have shown in the lab
لقد عرضنا في المعمل البحثي
that we can receive up to 50 megabytes per second
اننا نستطيع الاستقبال بسرعة حتى 50 ميجابايت /الثانية
from a standard, off-the-shelf solar cell.
من خلال خلية شمسية قياسية المواصفات
And this is faster than most broadband connections these days.
وهذا أسرع من معظم اتصالات النطاق العريض هذه الايام
Now let me show you in practice.
الان دعوني اعرض عليكم ذلك عمليا
In this box is a standard, off-the-shelf LED lamp.
في هذا الصندوق مصباح ليد قياسي
This is a standard, off-the-shelf solar cell;
وهذه خلية شمسية قياسية
it is connected to the laptop.
انها متصلة بجهاز الكمبيوتر المحمول
And also we have an instrument here
ولدينا ايضا جهاز هنا
to visualize the energy we harvest from the solar cell.
لاظهار الطاقة التي نحصل عليها من الخلية الشمسية
And this instrument shows something at the moment.
وهذا الجهاز يظهر شيئا حاليا
This is because the solar cell already harvests light from the ambient light.
و ذلك بسبب ان الخلية تحصل على الطاقة من الضوء المحيط بنا
Now what I would like to do first is switch on the light,
الان ما اريد فعله هو تشغيل الضوء
and I'll simply, only switch on the light,
فقط سوف اشغل الضوء بتلك البساطة
for a moment,
للحظة
and what you'll notice is that the instrument jumps to the right.
وما سوف تلاحظون هو تحرك المؤشر نحو اليمين
So the solar cell, for a moment,
لذا الخلية الشمسية وللحظة
is harvesting energy from this artificial light source.
تحصل على الطاقة من مصدر الضوء الصناعي
If I turn it off, we see it drops.
وعندما اطفيء، نرى المؤشر يقل
I turn it on ...
اشغل ثانية
So we harvest energy with the solar cell.
اذا نحن نحصل على الطاقة من الخلية الشمسية
But next I would like to activate the streaming of the video.
لكن الان اريد ان انشط البث الخاص بالفيديو
And I've done this by pressing this button.
وانا فعلت ذلك بالضغط على هذا الزر
So now this LED lamp here is streaming a video
اذا الان لمبة الليد هنا تقوم ببث الفيديو
by changing the brightness of the LED in a very subtle way,
من خلال تغيرات ضوء الليد بطريقة تقنية للغاية
and in a way that you can't recognize with your eye,
بشكل لا يمكن ان تلاحظوه باعينكم المجردة
because the changes are too fast to recognize.
لان التغيرات اسرع من ان تلاحظوها
But in order to prove the point,
لكن من اجل اثبات ذلك
I can block the light of the solar cell.
استطيع حجب الضوء عن الخلية الشمسية
So first you notice the energy harvesting drops
لذلك اول ما تلحظون هو انخفاض الطاقة المستخلصة
and the video stops as well.
ويتوقف بث الفيديو ايضا
If I remove the blockage, the video will restart.
اذا ازلت الحجب ، سوف يبدا الفيديو مرة اخرى
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And I can repeat that.
واستيطيع ان اكرر ذلك
So we stop the transmission of the video and energy harvesting stops as well.
لذلك نوقف البث الخاص بالفيديو والطاقة المستخلصة تتوقف ايضا
So that is to show that the solar cell acts as a receiver.
ولذلك لاظهار ان الخلية الشمسية تعمل كجهاز استقبال
But now imagine that this LED lamp is a street light, and there's fog.
لكن تخيل الان ان مصباح الليد هو مصباح بالشارع وهناك ضباب
And so I want to simulate fog,
ولذلك اريد ان احاكي الضباب
and that's why I brought a handkerchief with me.
ولذلك احضرت معي هذا المنديل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And let me put the handkerchief over the solar cell.
واسمحوا لي بوضع المنديل على الخلية الشمسية
First you notice
الاول تلاحظون
the energy harvested drops, as expected,
ان الطاقة المستخلصة تتوقف كما هو متوقع
but now the video still continues.
لكن الان الفيديو ما زال يعمل
This means, despite the blockage,
هذا يعني انه رغم الحجب
there's sufficient light coming through the handkerchief to the solar cell,
ان هناك ضوء كاف ياتي من خلال المنديل الى الخلية الشمسية
so that the solar cell is able to decode and stream that information,
لذلك تستطيع الخلية الشمسية ان تشفر وتبث المعلومات
in this case, a high-definition video.
في هذه الحالة ، فيديو عالي الوضوح
What's really important here is that a solar cell has become a receiver
ما يهم حقا هنا هو ان الخلية الشمسية تعمل كجهاز استقبال
for high-speed wireless signals encoded in light,
لاشارات لاسلكية عالية السرعة ومشفرة من خلال الضوء
while it maintains its primary function as an energy-harvesting device.
فيما تحتفظ بوظيفتها الاصلية وهي العمل كجهاز استخلاص الطاقة
That's why it is possible
ولذلك هذا ممكن
to use existing solar cells on the roof of a hut
ان تستخدم خلايا شمسية على سطح الكوخ
to act as a broadband receiver
لتعمل كجهاز استقبال للنطاق العريض
from a laser station on a close by hill, or indeed, lamp post.
من خلال محطة ليزر فوق هضبة مرتفعة او بالاحرى عمود اضاءة
And It really doesn't matter where the beam hits the solar cell.
ولا يهم حقا من اين ياتي الشعاع الواصل للخلية
And the same is true
وينطبق الشيء نفسه
for translucent solar cells integrated into windows,
على خلايا شمسية شفافة مدمجة بالنوافذ
solar cells integrated into street furniture,
خلايا شمسية مركبة بالمرافق العامة
or indeed, solar cells integrated into these billions of devices
او بالاحرى خلايا شمسية مدمجة في مليارات الادوات
that will form the Internet of Things.
والتي ستشكل انترنت الاشياء
Because simply,
لانه ببساطة
we don't want to charge these devices regularly,
لا نريد شحن هذه الاجهزة بانتظام
or worse, replace the batteries every few months.
او الاسوا استبدال البطاريات كل عدة شهور
As I said to you,
كما قلت لكم
this is the first time I've shown this in public.
هذه المرة الاولى التي اعرض هذا للعامة
It's very much a lab demonstration,
انه شيء خاص بالمعمل
a prototype.
نموذج
But my team and I are confident that we can take this to market
لكن نثق انا وفريقي اننا نستيطع ايصال ذلك للسوق الاستهلاكي
within the next two to three years.
في خلال السنتين او الثلاث القادمة
And we hope we will be able to contribute to closing the digital divide,
ونامل بان نكون ساهمنا في سد الفجوة الرقمية
and also contribute
وايضا ساهمنا
to connecting all these billions of devices to the Internet.
بايصال مليارات من الاجهزة للانترنت
And all of this without causing
وكل هذا دون التسبب
a massive explosion of energy consumption --
في استهلاك ضخم للطاقة
because of the solar cells, quite the opposite.
لان الخلايا الشمسية عكس ذلك تماما
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)